this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet SC radio is
brought to you by the I Triple E
Computer Society I Triple E software
magazine online a computer org slash
software well we've run two software
engineering radio today my name's Kim
Carter I'll be your host and today we've
got her own Mia is gist who and Mia is
the founder of flexed the company behind
the well-loved thanks canary tools
Haroon has contributed to civil bucks on
information security and has published a
number of papers on various topics
related to the field over the past
decade and a half
Haroon has delivered a research talks
and keynotes at conferences around the
world and there's quite a long list so
welcome to the show today her own thanks
for having me most types of security
exploitation have a network involved
somewhere even though in some cases that
may be abstracted the Yahoo data
breaches are a good example of this
reconnaissance which is the act of
information gathering
I generally utilizes the Internet at a
minimum application security generally
requires a network in order to access
the target applications cleared security
similarly depends on a network in order
to access our target resources social
engineering leverages a network of
people in order to access a human target
even physical security often involves
different types of networks today we're
going to be discussing the different
types of networks including the ones we
often don't think about what are your
assets an attacker may target what are
the risks to those assets and the types
of countermeasures we need to be
thinking about in order to mitigate the
risks there are some relevant articles
from the I Triple E Computer Society on
today's topic such as computer network
security and defense technology research
security defenses for vulnerable
amiracle sensor networks and the network
perspective of cloud security all found
at computer org slash CS DL we had a
show on dock
QT with Diego a moniker that was shown
number 290 and we've also looked at
bringing the security focus up front
with a show on DFC cops with Francis
Reynard there was shown number 288 now
the lines between the different types of
security that's physical people VPS
Network cloud application mobile in IOT
are sometimes blurred and in many cases
are being pushed to application security
and network security and often into the
cloud please start with some basic
questions rune what is network security
and what is application security and how
are they different all right I think at
its simplest network security is
policies procedures to protect network
connected resources and your application
security would be policies procedures
measures taken to improve the security
posture of your apps but having said
this the lines were a lot clearer ten to
fifteen years ago because these days
you've got infrastructure that's
actually software you've got Software
Defined everything and one of the things
that's plagued us historically from a
security point of view is you'll often
find that your infrastructure is
actually someone else's code and by this
I mean if you take it at its simplest
the network security would typically
worry about setting up your hosts
setting up your network while your
developers worked on the code that they
ran on those platforms but if you pon
date even the servers that you run on
was some software houses code right so
so so the lines blur interestingly and
increasingly they blur more and more
just as with any other form of security
the first thing we need to think about
is what's valuable to us in regards to a
network security
what are we attempting to protect and
why what area assets right so what's
interesting is a little while back
there's a really smart security guy
called FX who put out a paper and it's
it's worth checking out
was back in like 2014 he put a paper
called back to basics and one of the
interesting things that FX touches on in
that paper is he says that today we've
got to acknowledge that almost all the
systems we have actually composite
systems and then goes on to say that we
keep talking about security as if
there's a critical gate but you need to
understand that in a composite system
everything's a gate and so yeah it
becomes interesting to note that even if
you're dealing with with some level of
abstraction like you've got some ring
fence around you working on the code
what that code is running on matters how
reachable those hosts are matter how
many other parts there are to that host
matter what the dependencies of that
host are matter and yeah somebody's got
to be making sure that all of that stuff
is looked at and considered from a
security point of view the the stuff
that you just mentioned which is knowing
what assets you actually have is
surprisingly overlooked and surprisingly
not a well solved problem in in many
large enterprises you see companies now
trying to do this sort of thing with
asset management but in a previous life
for example we did a lot of network
based penetration testing and we'd spend
about 40% of an engagement just
footprinting the organization just
figuring out what they had and where
they had it because often we've managed
to break in not because of some cunning
zero-day but just because we're able to
find some step into their network that
they didn't know still existed yes a
good reconnaissance right yeah
absolutely yeah one of the comments I
received recently was as a software
engineer do I really care about physical
network security
why should software engineers care yeah
so I think this goes back a little bit
to effects this point about the security
of a composite system it doesn't matter
how secure your code is if you're
building it on a house of cards you're
gonna have a bad day
so yeah ultimately it comes down to the
security of your of your application and
if your applications being made insecure
because of design choices or
architecture choices they effectively
beneath you in the stack then that
stuff's going to have a very real impact
on you and I guess it depends ultimately
on on what you trying to do in your job
or in your career you could probably
take the view that says I swim in my
lane and don't care about anything else
but but if you plan to ship code that
stands up to the reasonable attack you
probably need to at least understand the
basics the other thing is software
engineers we're actually building
networks in the cloud with with
configuration is carried right
increasingly using configuration as code
and increasingly using the law you've
mentioned that you've spoken to sector
of opsin or at least DevOps folks and
increasingly those lines blur completely
and and one of the things to keep in
mind is with us as pen testers or even
just as attackers doesn't all quote that
that essentially says that we basically
love between the cracks so so it's
anywhere that that these cracks appear
either when it's two systems that are
joining together or two roles in an
organization that joined together it's
perfectly the place where where
attackers and pen testers love yeah
what's changed with computer network
security over the last five to ten years
depends on how cynical you are on any
given day so so the super cynical answer
is not enough and mainly you say that
because pretty famously old pen testers
like to point out that you can slow on
most customer networks just like it's
the early 2000s
so there's slope or segmentation they
still look poor design choice
is proliferating there the ray of
sunshine through all of this is would
move to cloud people had the opportunity
to react attacked would the move to
things like Google's beyond cope you
starting to see the promise of new
designs and an almost with the new type
of containerization and micro services
you starting to see a different
architecture image that maybe gives us
some hope and one of the big things is
some vendors have learnt their lessons
so in the early 2000s network hosts you
could go on to any network in own
Microsoft boxes with a vast array of of
exploits Microsoft's been working pretty
hard for the last 15 years to make sure
that their hosts were reasonably harder
and now you're starting to see the
promise of hosts that actually stand up
pretty well like like if you look at
where n of hot Android god no if you
starting to look at where Google
Chromebooks are going or where iOS is
going you starting to see the promise of
hosts that can stand up to a reasonable
attack by skilled attackers here's the
shift of their Alliance that your
average attacker used to have on network
security exploitation skills to other
areas such as cloud services application
security and of course people and if so
how so yeah so so I think there's always
a shift like ooze so there's two parts
to this right oh the one part is the bad
news and the bad news there is that
attackers are always shifting and
they're able to do it a little bit
quicker because they get to cherry-pick
their knowledge so they get to do deep
dives just on bits that give them super
great wins while defenders have to do
some of the boring infrastructure bits
because they need to be done and so yeah
there's definitely been a move you've
seen attackers move up
to the application stack because over
the last while applications become the
gateways to two networks and essentially
to the crown jewels so so a long time
ago before web app started proliferating
but there was the concept that maybe
people could shut down their networks
and not permit much and more and more
people started opening applications up
to the world and now a web server is the
interface essentially to the database
back-end so attackers don't need to own
your network and map out your network
and find where the database server is
and obtain creds and log in to steal the
data he just needs to find the flaw in
your web application because that's
making those database calls anyway so on
the one end stuff has certainly moved
towards the a player social engineering
is as old as it gets but it never goes
away
and one of the reasons it never goes
away is because it's so shockingly
effective pen testers like to act like
they're really skilled at at social
engineering but the simple answer is
it's just an easy game to win when we
were pen testing company we literally
had to stop our junior pen testers from
taking things too far because once they
figured out that they could just lie and
cheat and win on pen test engagements
they literally started outdoing
themselves with the outrageous stuff
they could get away with like literally
you had guys stealing entire computers
and databases from Target sites because
the target would walk them in it makes
for a fun job here does according to FBI
investigators are the likely avenue of
infiltration of the Yahoo internal
network was with a spear phishing email
to semi privileged unsuspecting
inadvertent Yahoo employee the
successful Spearfish allowed the
attackers direct access to Yahoo's
internal network what are you thoughts
about the fact that the
take it just about always still need to
network in order to access their target
whether the initial foothold be physical
people VPS as Network components or
whatever yeah so look without showing
for the product we we sell like like I
think it's a stupid problem that so many
years into it attack still looks so
similar to how all the texted and and
like if you take that entry vector which
is somebody gets fished they get
compromised and from that point they
move laterally into a network find the
juicy stuff and then run away with it
that stuff reads like any pen test
report from the late 90s or 2000s and
the truth is that still how most attacks
look against most people and yeah it
that stuff's not going away for a long
time like people with big hulking legacy
networks are still running what would
exactly those sorts of problems and for
the most part a little while back the
industry started pivoting and saying
listen we can't stop every vector like
either you're gonna fish Jim from
accounting or you going to give Jim from
accounting a USB disk on his cover of
golf monthly or you're going to only met
the coffee shop and he's gonna walk the
malware into the organization like
there's a squillion
entry points because Jimmy's jump what
we should do instead is move to the
point where we can detect it quickly
enough and contain it quickly enough so
you're not playing this constant game of
catch-up with attack vectors which which
really dominated network and and host
security guys thinking in the early
2000s we really thought that we could
patch our way out of that problem and
and then people started saying hey
listen that's just increased complexity
and and and that complexity problem just
gets worse and worse and worse right
like I gave a talk a few years ago where
I tried to point out
how complexity is just gonna keep giving
us clay here and and the stuff you can
pick up on is ridiculous like the three
quick examples that come to mind uh a
little while back
the guys from one of the Mac houses so
it's not even a security shop took a
hacksaw to one of these video adapters
because it wasn't giving them the
results they expected and they found
that there's a system on a chip in this
in your adapters with two gigs of ram so
literally your video transcoder came or
your video adapter is another computer
and and a little while after that one of
the guys from CrowdStrike
published research that showed that
every modern monitor actually has a x86
processor running in that and and then
just to top it off a bunny Huang the the
guy who's done the famous Xbox hacks a
few years ago to the talk where he
showed that this tiny processors on SD
cards that can be refreshed and
reprogrammed so so literally these 20
cent pieces of plastic are actually
little computers and so the complexity
and the number of vectors are off the
charts and so instead what you've got to
do is figure out that you've got all
these pieces that you can't trust that
could be compromised from a bunch of
different ways what you need to do is
have containment and detection so that
you know when stuff is behaving
abnormally or you realize when when
stuff is getting really horrible and you
can then react to it and and take it
from there
so have you got some tips around there
like around containment and detection I
mean here we go about doing name this is
a straight up layup yeah so so look
there's there's a guy called Marcus
Ranum
and Marcus Ranum wrote the first disk
file firewall like many moons ago so at
this point Marcus is still incredibly
smart incredibly insightful but an
incredible kamuran because he looks at
everything and says well I told you guys
what to do 20
years ago why aren't you doing it yet
and he normally goes back to real basics
well have tiered architecture have
organized your networks this way you
should know if any of your servers make
an outbound connection and well Marc is
incredibly smart one of the things that
you figure out is if nobody is doing
this then like you fighting human nature
something stopping them from doing this
and one of the things that that we do as
a company is rebuild these tiny devices
that live on your network we call them
Canaries off from the old canary in a
coal mine and and part of what canary
does is you drop it on your network in a
bunch of different locations and the
whole logic is that when an attacker
breaks into your network and then starts
this lateral movement at that point the
attack has got to go through a type of
internal reconnaissance phase and
inadvertently what he does is ends up
touching one of your Canaries so the
canary becomes a simple low-cost way to
figure out that someone in on your
network is now touching things that he
shouldn't be touching but without
without pumping our own product a part
of the simple logic for for containment
and and detection like that is to have
different trust zones right like like at
this point there's no excuse on a
traditional network to not have
different trust zones and and I say on a
traditional network because the whole
Google beyond cope thing is something
that payers mentioned we should probably
circle circle around to at some point
but but on a traditional network there's
really no excuse if I compromised a
server in your DMZ that server should
never be initiating connections to
anyone or or if it is there's a short
list of servers it should be talking to
but what most pen testers and what most
attackers will tell you is you attack
one machine and that very quickly leads
to the ability to touch other machines
for the ability to exfiltrate data and
yeah that's that's where lots of
people's nightmares end up coming from
can you explain what network
segmentation is in in what are some of
the risks that are likely to occur if a
well-thought-out segmentation isn't
implemented right so so what
segmentation essentially the logic that
you're going for is that you you
classing your servers your users in into
zones of different trusts essentially
you saying look I need these servers to
be touching the internet and therefore I
assign a certain level of tint to them
in my head like I'm going to assume that
at some point the server could get
popped because it is exposed to users to
the unwashed Internet and and then you
have your database service and you'd say
ok I'm going to allow only the web
server to talk to this database farm and
this database farm should never be able
to initiate connections elsewhere and
and of course the problem with this is a
networks atrophy so even a well-designed
network today and three months has gone
through various iterations of just plug
it in and make it work and and in the
enterprise people are rewarded for
making stuff work not necessarily making
stuff secure so so people over time just
end up with situations where you've got
one big flat network even if you
originally tried some level of
segmentation that stuff quickly
disappears but but with the original
model or the original thinking you'd
have these different zones and then
you'd have some sort of alerting
when cross zone communication was going
to happen so so it's really easy to tell
if one of your web servers suddenly
tried to initiate a connection with a
host in China because none of your web
servers should be trying outbound
connections and that's the original
logic but it's surprisingly missing in
in in the real world apparently most of
your IOT devices need to have internet
access yeah IOT I'm sure at some point
you'll get an IOT specialist on but but
IOT one of the things that it seems to
be do you know it seems to do two things
like it seems to be bringing back all
our fun bugs from the 90s and the other
thing is it'll it seems to be bringing
back all the poor design decisions that
we we made in the 90s and yeah if if
you've got these IOT devices that
require direct connections I know some
organizations are putting them on a
separate network but then what you find
is you have a ot devices that bridge
both networks because they also
enrolling in Active Directory or also
hopping on to your wireless LANs and I
think for the most part this goes back
to my question of complexity like you
didn't think that your kettle needed to
be included in your threat model but it
increasingly looks like it probably
should be yeah it seems like one of the
problems also is that little thoughts
being put into our building security
into the actual components yeah
would that be your take as well yeah
it's it's it's interesting like like
it's something that people have been
complaining about for a long time and I
think they're in truth like there's a
much deeper issue right like like it's
it's really easy for us to say the
thoughts not being put in but but like
if you reasonable at some point you stop
and say well hold on why is nobody
putting this thought into it and you get
into a dark grey place then because what
you figure out is it's just economics
right and there's very little incentive
to do it right because the market
doesn't seem to reward that the market
currently seems to reward the people who
get there first and claim the land and
so there's a few people who are who are
big proponents of some sort of software
liability
I'm not quite sure where I sit on it
because in part the reason we managed to
get the internet to where it is in just
a few years is because you had browsers
that accepted anything and we had
fifteen-year-old kids writing Internet
Banking and Internet pay cart systems so
yeah it's it's it's an interesting one
because to get to the incentives it
seems like you're going to have to get
to the point where there's some sort of
liability talk but I suspect that that
in turn hampers innovation also and and
so we're gonna have to figure out a way
to get that right here would you
I'm gonna be providing a network
segmentation for IOT devices you've got
any thoughts around it before for IOT
specifically um I looked this advice
would go into almost any question like
this like like typically what you'd look
at is what the what the object in
question needs to access and like I say
if we go back to my question on
detection the question would be what do
I need to do to tell if this thing turns
rogue like if if this thing turns evil
what can it get at right now or how bad
can it get and then the second part
would be would I know if this thing
turned evil or became someone's proxy so
in general with with IOT I'd try to keep
it isolated off the company network or
off the company's cope Network and if it
needed access to the COPE network I'd at
least want to know what it's doing
you're starting to get and and I don't
think products are generally the answer
link like I think understanding your
threat model and then designing well is
is generally your best step but I know
they are products right laughs right now
like like the guys that scenario have a
product that you drop on your network
and they then watch for your IOT traffic
and then use machine learning to try to
tell you when one of those devices start
talking in a way that they don't
normally talk
but for the most part my my pitch there
would be that you'd have to design the
security in from a network point of view
to cater for the fact that the vendor
probably hasn't know my son is like a
lost cause
for the most part parts of it like like
part of the okay we're now going to do
containment and detection like some
people do see that as a little bit
fatalist because they'd like to believe
that actually you can harden every
device against attack and for the most
part I'm willing to bet that that's a
failing strategy and one you'd
permanently fail on and instead my
suggestion like I said is almost always
to aim for way that you can get some
sort of network segregation in place and
then some sort of network detection in
place to know when air quotes bad stuff
is happening I'm just gonna move into a
bit of a discussion I'm around the
fortress or candy bar mentality
so this is where organizations believe
that all the attackers are on the
outside of the organization and those on
the inside are trustworthy now what are
your thoughts around this oh well for
the one thing it's it's what kept most
pen testers and attackers looking smart
all of these years right because it's
essentially the attacker gets his one
foothold into the network and at that
point is on the soft and chewy inside
and no longer from the hardened crust
crunchy exterior and and like I say that
thinking is so pervasive that attacking
lots of these networks just doesn't look
very different to attacking these
networks in the late 90s like once you
inside the network you exposed to all of
these hosts that have never been patched
or woefully out-of-date you exposed to
too horrible trust relationships it
basically becomes shooting fish in a
barrel and again the if
if you take what what I've said
repeatedly the the fact that there are
so many vectors into a network these
days the logic that says we can afford
to be soft on the inside is just not a
realistic one
it's where solutions like Google's
beyond cop I mentioned Bianco perfu
tangents it's probably worth at least a
two line overview beyond cop is Google's
implementation of a parameter less
network what and and obviously it's it's
a whole new paradigm and and it requires
a lot of architecting and a lot of
thinking if someone moves to a beyond
cop infrastructure the essential logic
is that there's no difference between a
user who's sitting at his desk at HQ or
sitting at a coffee shop or working from
home there's no inherent trust that
one's location makes a difference and
you can see why why Google would go
there because if you architect for a
world where you no longer trust the
network especially then you've got to
harder than the other parts of your
network like you should or the other
parts of your system like you should and
so Google's documented their
implementation of this pretty
extensively in a few papers like I say
they call it beyond cop it's it's
certainly worth checking out for for
users for listeners who are interested
in that sort of thing
the IBM x-force cyber security
intelligence index research is a large
number of organizations each year and
they've extracted some interesting data
or Mesilla some of the earlier years but
2015 it's 60% of all attacks were
carried out by insiders 44.5% were
malicious inside actors and 15.5% were
inadvertent inside actors in 2016 we see
30 percent of all attacks were carried
out by insiders seven percent were
malicious and side actors 23% were
inadvertent inside actors
the Yahoo data breach in many others
everyday confirmed that a large
percentage of all security breaches come
from within the organization's walls do
you think that this is an indicator that
our workers are succumbing to an
increased number of social engineering
attacks by outside it the tech is
attempting to get their payloads inside
the organization's networks yeah look
like I said the the social engineering
stuffs going to be around for a long
time because it's that easy
and it's that effective if you talk to
any of the hard core security
researchers who've been doing the a deep
application security or or researching
on complex next-generation attacks for
like 15 years you'll often find them
with with tears in their eyes because
they've spent all this time working on
advanced memory corruption attacks that
work in the face of built-in compiler
mitigations and OS mitigations and and
they managed to find ways to hijack
execution flow and actually you've got
all these networks falling down to
effectively someone mailing them saying
please transfer money or please give me
access to your network and it's not
works so for sure social engineering is
still shockingly effective and a lot of
people believe that the answer is to
train your way out of it I think there's
something to be said for training your
staff like it beats having a completely
untrained staff but for the most part
again I think what we need to get to is
architecting solutions for them that
don't require them to do the right thing
and the slides a little bit in the face
of lots of people's thoughts let's say
you need to train your users and educate
your users because they're your best
defense like in truth for any
non-trivial sized company I think you're
going to have some Chi in accounts or
some lady in marketing
who's not gonna get that URL reads like
trustworthiness reads from left to right
and not right to left so secure the bank
calm is not the same as calm the bank
dot secure which is a completely
different domain and the number of
tricks that you can pull like that like
it's completely ridiculous to believe
that you could you could tell a user all
of these tricks like you get people who
go well just teach them to haul over the
link in Outlook but but that's kind of
naive there's there's a squillion ways
to convince someone why that link is
genuine a from just implementing network
trickery but B even just the fact that
social engineering relies on people and
and convincing people to to do stuff for
you and fundamentally we social social
beings and want to help each other for
our listeners can you define what
command and control is sure so so
normally people talk about command and
control when they've compromised the
host so you've compromised a host or a
series of hosts and and you now need
some way to talk to that host remotely
and and so traditionally these
compromised hosts would have some sort
of command and control channel that goes
back to the internet or goes back to the
attacker somehow so that they can now
communicate with these compromised hosts
on your network and over the years
you've seen that evolve and get cleverer
and cleverer hoping like if networks get
better designed you'd need more cunning
command and control channels to try and
effectively control the hosts that you
own on their target network again it's
it's one of those things that are almost
a losing game for defenders unless
they've really got their segmentation
done right and got their
done right over the years we've pulled
some ridiculous tricks to to get out of
even tightly controlled networks yeah
it's it's an attackers game for sure
so here can we stop insiders and
Outsiders connecting to our network
access points in proliferating malware
commanding control clients etc onto our
corporate networks so so if you're
talking about malicious insiders yeah
it's like like no matter what anyone
tells you like if there's an insider who
really wants to do bad stuff and he's
got some measure of access it's gonna be
really hard for you to stop him like
like if he's crew though and and so so
if you take the thought of a of a
command-and-control channel at this
point almost everyone's heard of Stuxnet
but but many moons before Stuxnet we did
an assessment on a client network and
the client believed that they were
completely safe because they were on a
completely air-gapped Network and all we
did on their network was we wrote some
software that when it was on their
machine would steal all of their data
and then wait till a USB was plugged in
the USB stick was plugged in and and
when a USB stick was plugged in it would
then hop onto the USB stick and every
time that USB stick was plugged in
somewhere else the first thing it would
do was check if it had access to the
Internet and if it had access to the
Internet
would then post all of the that data to
the comments of some blog site um so
effectively it would hop onto USB sticks
hoping somebody would carry it out of
the network at some point and it worked
and to the same end if I'm a malicious
binary running on your network I've got
a bunch of options to try to find my way
out of your network people talk about
DNS exfiltration effectively instead of
making a direct connection to the
internet making DNS requests and passing
my traffic through valid DNS traffic but
actually there's there's a host of
different
so effectively what you'd want is tight
control of your endpoints and again
detection of outbound traffic so that
you'd know when silliness like this was
happening on your network on the topic
of exfiltration infiltration what are
some of the techniques and tools
commonly used yeah so so if we talk
about infiltration there's a number of
ways into your network right so you've
mentioned phishing a few times and and
again it's it's painful how stupid and
successful that is like like you
literally just a step removed from
mailing someone a file and saying please
run this file like it's it's only
slightly more abstract than that so
instead you're sending them an excel
file which asks them to enable macros or
you sending them some other file format
that they didn't know actually mask
executable content and again as a
throwback or the problem here the root
problem is complexity right because it
turns out that every excel file can
actually embed shockwave flash which can
actually run content on the user's
machine so yeah getting in this there's
a bunch of ways so either you get in
because you've fished someone or you get
in because you've managed to infect
something in these guys supply chain so
somewhere on the internal network
they're running a binary that they think
they can trust but they actually
shouldn't or you've compromised some
service so so through the internet
you've attacked some application and and
if you take a simple attack out of the
2000s if there's a standard lamp service
or the web app that's sitting there and
and you managed to get yourself a sequel
injection attack going well now you
executing code on the database server
and so as an attacker you you your view
now pivots right it doesn't matter that
you sitting on the outside of the
network
once you execute code as the database
server you become the database server
and and your view is anything that the
database server sees and your
credentials or anything that the
database server has control of and we
spent as pen testers we spent stupid
amounts of time making that stuff
comfortable for ourselves so so if if
you imagine a standard sequel injection
attack in around 2009 we had two kids
pulled for self that if we could pull
off sequel injection against your server
then we could pretty much load a proxy
on our network that would essentially
tunnel complete TCP traffic through that
sequel injection attack to the other
side of your network so so if you had an
RDP server inside your network that your
sequel server could talk to because of
the sequel injection attack we could
literally just RDP from our network
straight through to the RDP server on
the inside of your network and that data
would be passing through your web server
through the database server and then
going out as a TCP stream and and that's
why I say at that point it's only down
to how creative your attacker is he'll
find a path through that and if we take
a just a moment more on that just
because it's it's worth noting how much
attackers do what with how little access
if you take the standard sequel
injection attack from the 2002 's I put
in bad data in your form field it gets
passed off to your sequel server your
sequel server then interprets this as
sequel code and I just puts back to a
page that I can read or splits back an
error message that I can now use as an
Oracle to figure out what's going on and
so what you started getting were people
who are incredibly good or tools that
were incredibly good at pulling data
of a sequel server from webpage error
messages and people started figuring out
that you don't send debug messages back
fraud and and so then what attackers
started doing they started figuring out
different ways to get that data out and
and again around 2008 I think we did a
talk that we called pushing the camel
through the eye of the needle for one
thing because we extremely bared at
choosing talk titles but essentially
what we were going for was new ways to
get data in and out of networks and and
so if you take that progression with
what the first attack we're eating error
messages the second one I already
touched on is I can find a way to tell
your sequel server to do a DNS lookup
okay and if we sticking with sequel
server there's a bunch of ways I can
make your sequel server do a DNS lookup
your for one thing you did your sequel
server has stored procedures that take
UNC paths as parameters so I can tell it
we used run the stored procedure and the
UNC path is me calm your sequel server
then has to resolve that UNC path it
does a DNS request for me calm and so if
I'm looking at my DNS server logs I can
now tell that someone just did a look up
for me calm and and if you take that as
a simple primitive that says I can make
you do a DNS lookup and view the results
you can see where that goes right I can
start saying well okay tell me what
files on your machine and for every file
that's on your machine do a lookup for
file name me calm and and then sitting
on my DNS server I see requests coming
in for a door bat at me calm and
windowed I&I at me calm and and of
course that's just a very basic way of
doing it what you'd quickly get to is
the point where you'd say let's encode
this data so that we can make it binary
say
and then do the lookup and so we built
toolkits so that you'd be able to do
that and completely transfer binaries
through DNS if you needed to and and the
only thing that's happening there is the
sequel server is making DNS requests
like the only thing that would be
visible there is that sequel server
making DNS requests and and to go back
to the question then on what should be
happening one of the things that you'd
often find out is your sequel server
does not need to make DNS requests or
certainly doesn't need a DNS resolver
that talks all the way to the Internet
and so that extra functionality should
be getting cut just to labor that point
for four people on tired of it yet if
DNS requests was a cool-looking stunt to
get data out sometime later we figured
out that you could essentially run your
sequel injection attack and so so we
started bumping into networks where even
DNS wasn't allowed out and even they're
worth a little bit of effort and outside
the box thinking what we we figure is
well what I can do is I can tell your
sequel server sleep ten and if I can
tell your sequel server to sleep ten or
I can give it a computationally
intensive command to run I can look at
your web server or your web app and see
that it's become unresponsive for ten
seconds and so again that becomes a
primitive so we can say list the files
on your system if your file is a dot
that take the first character it's an A
which is binary 1 101 one one if it's a
one sleep tin if it's a zero sleep zero
and then read the amount of times or the
durations that your app is unresponsive
for and essentially you then get a
timing channel and because we building
tools all the time to make this stuff
easy at the end of it you have a tool
that essentially lets you choose what's
your communication channel with this
host and you say
error messages or you say DNS or you say
timing and then you never have to think
about it again
that thing's abstracted away from for
you and it's essentially just you and
what you want to do what are some of the
countermeasures we could put in place to
stop these types of attacks happening
yes so so a text like that um there's
there's multiple things that can be done
to protect against it and to detect it
like like in that one I was talking
sequel injection and essentially sequel
injection is a essentially a dev problem
right like like what you need to be
doing is using bind variables or not
just concatenating sequel queries that
users give you and throwing untrusted
input at your database server so so
there's good solutions for all of these
individual problems but but I think the
takeaway if nothing else other than
completely annoying your your listeners
to take away that that your listeners
should take is is s attack as we spend
an incredible amount of time working on
really small cracks and it's literally
where the attackers play is is finding
these really small holes and turning
them into beachheads that we can use to
attack the rest of the network so so in
that case it's secure development
practice right to prevent the sequel
injection attack in the first place its
network segmentation and architecture to
make sure that if we're running commands
on your database server we don't have
easy access out because we resort to
timing and DNS when we can't make a
direct connection out and and so the
trick is to make it increasingly hard
for attackers so either they move on
because you're not worth the effort or
you find ways to trip them up so that
you can actually detect them and and
then start hunting for them I mean we've
been telling software engineers for
after years I need to put themselves
into the shoes of the attacker but I'm
not sure that that's actually working
because
lot of software engineers can't think
like the attackers so I mean no again
and it's it's it's it's countered to a
whole bunch of documentation but um
there's a real smart guy called Adam
szostak who works for Microsoft um who
did a lot of thinking and writing about
this and and he said telling developers
to think like attackers is about as
effective as telling someone why don't
you think like a chef and and he says go
just tell someone bake a nice cake think
like a chef um
and the answer is its it's not
prescriptive enough right like for for
the stuff that I'm that I was telling
you about to the point where you
tunneling data through a sequel
injection through timing attacks it's
it's essentially unfair because we've
spent a whole lot of time on that really
niche part of the problem while your
defenders or your coders are busy
working to different deadlines and so
yeah I don't think they could quite do
that I think there is value in in doing
threat modeling with your users and with
your coders and and if there's anything
uh like if there's any one thing that I
think developers should be doing is
making sure they sitting with their
security teams or amongst themselves
doing threat modeling so figuring out
where attacks are likely to come from
what the attacks likely to look like and
and the good thing that that threat
modeling does is it allows you to prune
entire classes or entire areas of attack
right so so it doesn't matter that you
don't know every type of sequel
injection attack that's out there but
you you kind of get to the point where
you can say well let's assume there's a
tak a that is running commands on this
database server how would we contain it
how would we detect it and and sometimes
you end up what what broad solutions
then that end up saving you but but for
sure it's something that the team needs
to sit down and think about
design tab in high security environments
unlike Yahoo what I found is that many
of the common application security
defects and attacks don't work in the
attacker has to resort to attacking
hosts networks physical premises and of
course people is in social engineering
them can you explain your experience
around how high security environments
differ from the average or low security
environments yeah okay so so my honest
answer is it's really easy for for
people to point it Yahoo and companies
like that and laugh when they get popped
but for the most part one of the dirty
secrets of most security guys is almost
everyone sitting in in pretty horrible
positions hoping that when the attacks
happen the attacks don't happen on their
watch you starting to see organizations
that come through now what that are
making smart design choices and and like
like I must stress here that it's it's
still the exception rather than the norm
to find guys that are actually doing
this stuff right and and you starting to
see smart companies now like like slack
or Etsy or stripe and docker and where
they've essentially taken really smart
security guys and bolt them into their
product teams and and so what you
starting to see is hardened
infrastructures from the get-go where
we're smart design choices mean that
your security teams are actually
building infrastructure that's safer for
other people to use rather than standing
about telling them what they should do
but to go back to your question how do
the high security ones differ from the
low security ones it's the thing that
I'd keep coming back to is on high
security networks they'd figure out you
were there when you were there as
opposed to most average networks like
like the stat from from most of these
response companies and Microsoft and
guys like that now that most companies
only figure out they've been compromised
between 200 and 300 days after the
initial compromise and and in truth
that's that's even worse because most of
these guys figure out they compromised
because the data is kind of self
advertising so so target figures out
they compromised because someone's using
credit card data that was target's
credit card data in Mexico but if the
information itself didn't advertise hey
every stolen then it would unknown for
an even longer period and sometimes you
don't know it until another country puts
up a Joint Strike Fighter that looks a
lot like your Joint Strike Fighter and
yeah so so it that's a pretty horrible
place to be in and unfortunately it's
more than norm then it should be like um
there's a keynote by Alex Thomas who is
the CEO of Facebook currently and I
suspect he was actually the CEO of Yahoo
when he gave this talk which is super
interesting but in his talk he basically
said if if you took the fortune 500 you
could take a hundred of the top hundred
in that fortune 500 and say these guys
know how to play the security game not
they involve all they know how to play
the game and he said the next 400 like
in his slide deck he referred to them as
the toast of the 400 he said like these
guys are broken and they don't know that
they've broken for for all of these
reasons and yeah it's certainly job
security for four people in the InfoSec
field but it's pretty grim if you don't
have visibility as to what's happening
on your network at all levels then
chances are things are happening that
you don't want happening the unknown
attacks that target each of the network
layers what
some of the attacks that we need
visibility on yeah so so visibility is
an interesting one right because for a
little while all of these companies
popped up selling seem equipment and and
they took a fundamentally good message
which is you need visibility on your
network and used it to sell a whole
bunch of gear that just logged
everything and threw everything into
data lakes and what people are finding
out now as you enter gardeners trough of
Illusion disillusionment on the hype
cycle is that just collecting everything
also isn't some sort of silver bullet
and and so like I'm going to push
slightly against the guys who like
there's a crowd out there who say long
everything because the more data you
have the the more useful it is and by
analogy
you'll note by super weird analogy
collect everything was the happened to
be the catchphrase of the NSA when when
in a post 9/11 world and and one of the
things that become apparent through the
Snowden leaks is that logging everything
wasn't particularly effective I'm sure
you had all this data and at some point
some data store knew that terrorists a
spoke to terrorist be last week but if
it's hidden in haystacks of other
haystacks of needles you don't know that
you've got this data and it's not
actionable and and so again my almost
shortcut solution for this is that when
designing visibility and detection
systems like that it's a good time to
get in an attacker who actually knows
what he's doing so so they they talk
about they used to talk about red teams
and blue teams where red teams were the
attackers and blue teams were the
defenders and recently there's a rise of
what they call purple teamers so guys
working on both and and it's one of the
good times I feel to get in a purple
team
to kind of tell you look so so a you do
your threat modeling or B you take this
guy and you say look what are the
possible ways you're going to break into
this thing and then you spend a good
amount of time saying well okay for each
of the things that this guy is said how
would we notice that thing happening and
so you you do you design your you're
monitoring and you're alerting around
the things that would have given this
guy away or caught this guy and and then
although one of the things that people
have been spending lots of money on for
the last few years is penetration
testing network penetration testing and
it's not been largely effective if if
you couple that with this detection or
with this mindset you start to see some
winds where on every pen tested
engagement you can then go take the
report and say not just remediate the
findings that the guy is used to break
in but for every step go well how could
I have spotted this early enough or how
could have spotted this guy at this
stage and and then you come up with
essentially ways to to disrupt that
attackers flow and so inadvertently you
end up what would ways of of detecting
bigger classes of problems or yeah which
is exactly what you want to do what do
software engineers now need to
understand about computer network
technologies in order to mitigate
attackers using them as a channel to
assist exploiting areas of a business in
gaining access to their assets so I
think there's a few things that are
worth knowing
though the start point I think from from
everything that I've said and and I
mentioned before is just that attackers
will spend an incredible amount of time
trying to leverage really small things
to get bigger things so so it's one of
those things where you you really have
to be careful like like one set of creds
found on
a development box has been the start of
unraveling many a fine Network because
it's it's one set of creds for one
database either you getting goodness in
that database or you're now running with
the role of that database and that stuff
spreads like crazy but but aside for
that there's there's a bunch of just
basic hygiene that developers need to be
thinking about like like in this day and
age it's gonna sound completely stupid
considering we've just been talking
in-depth about network security but but
there's a few common things that users
should be doing it at this point if
you're not using a password manager it's
ridiculous because password reuse is is
stupidly popular and as an attacker it's
just such an incredible gift like if you
own the guy and know that his creds are
gonna work on every other system in the
network it's an absolute pleasure and
and then actually starting to use
equipment that's that's more more
resistant to attack so at this point
iOS is reasonably well locked down we've
got pretty good proxies for identifying
the the difference in cost of attacking
an iOS device versus attacking an
Android device so so if you're going to
have a system that effectively is the
key to your entire AWS infrastructure
maybe it shouldn't be on a jailbroken
iPhone or on our Android device that you
also play a flappy bird with and and so
I think there's there's little things
like that or little hygiene things like
that that developers should be thinking
about aside from obviously development
security best practice which I'm
assuming everyone is keeping relatively
up-to-date with and listening to their
security teams with could you just give
us a bit of a intro
and to what the canary tolls our and how
they work
sure so so essentially there's two
components the one is a throwback to the
90s like everything else I've said and
and that's the fact that we have a pitch
that says that honey pots were a good
idea but they were actually a good idea
for breach detection so so not for
studying your attacker and not for
confusing your attacker if you take any
of the discussion that we've had so far
our thesis is that if an attacker
compromises a host on your DMZ one of
his early steps is going to be looking
around your DMZ for other hosts and so
our logic is wouldn't it be nice if
there was a box on on your DMZ that
looked attractive for your organization
looked attractive to an attacker but let
you know out-of-band at the moment it
was touched and and the logic is that
only an attacker would be touching it
and it it comes back to something
interesting which is a mistake we've
been making in the industry for a really
long time and that's if you look at
traditional detection mechanisms like
intrusion detection IDs and IPSS these
products have always demoed really well
but not really worked so well in
enterprises and the reason for that is
because most attacks in reality don't
look like a text they just look like
normal usage so so these ideation IPS is
when the guy gives the demo and runs an
attack tool on them they light up and
you know that there's an attack and it's
all great but when it's on your network
the attacker browsing your network just
looks like a user browsing your network
and so the IDS and IPS is silent and so
what these Canadian honey pots aim to do
is almost reverse that which is normal
users shouldn't ever touch them because
they've got no cause to but an attacker
was unfamiliar with the terrain is going
to be looking around he doesn't know
what's legit and what isn't he touches
them and they give you the alarm and and
so what we've done with
but the canary is we've made that a
ridiculously easy for people to deploy
so so the logic is safe if honey pots
for breach detection were a good idea
why aren't people doing it and the
answer is because if they've got to
manage a thousand nodes on the network
we can't tell them the solution is
please add these 20 nodes except they
fake so so what canary allows you to do
is deploy mixed into activities so honey
pots that like if if you make it a lamp
so it really looks like a lamp server
and runs a webserver and runs my sequel
or if you make it a Windows share it
really has an SMB share with fake files
on it that you can dress up but all of
that you get to set up in three minutes
so so our pitch is you should be able to
drop it in minutes and walk away from it
and at some point it's gonna call out to
you because someone's touched it and
then you know that you should cancel
your plans so so that's the one
component which is these canary honey
pots and then we've got something called
canary tokens so if if your listeners go
and this is completely free if they go
to canary tokens org essentially what
you'll see there is infrastructure so
that people can deploy Canadian tokens
or honey tokens so so the logic is
totally simple you'd go to the site and
you'd say I want a web token okay if we
take the simplest example and what you
do then is you put in your email address
and you put in a reminder so so I'll put
in a reminder that says mum's Gmail okay
and and the system will then give you a
unique URL and and what I'll do is I'll
take that URL and put it in the first
mail in my mom's Gmail in her inbox and
the logic is that at some point when
someone breaks into my mom's account and
is reading her email they're going to go
to mail number one they're going to see
this link and either they browser
or they click on it and at that point
the system sends a mail to that mail
address to my mail address to tells me
somebody just clicked on mom's even on
on the canary token that was mom's email
and and now that token is the simplest
one right where we give you a URL we can
also give you a unique domain name and
the moment someone looks up that domain
name you'd get an alert and with those
two primitives we can build incredibly
complex tokens so we can give you a word
doc and the moment that word doc is
opened it would go out and say this word
doc has just been opened from this IP
address or a PDF file and and so
essentially we start giving you all
these little tokens that you can spread
about on your network or spread about on
your machines and completely forget
about them right because it's not
something you have to actively monitor
but the alert becomes self-identifying
so so take that PDF file and when you
create it you create it and say dad's
Dropbox and essentially take that PDF
file
keep it on Dad's Dropbox and forget
about it and four years from now when
dad's compromised and someone double
clicks the PDF from his Dropbox you get
a message telling you someone just
clicked on dad's Dropbox PDF
here's his IP address and again what
you're looking for is that early warning
so you not in that 300 day Club and and
so over time we keep adding canary token
so so the last token that we added for
example is an AWS API token so
essentially you'd come to the site and
you'd say my name is Bob at Bob calm and
this is a fake AWS API token that I'm
keeping on my spare laptop and you click
generate and we'll give you a set of AWS
API keys take those API keys and store
them on your safe laptop because when an
attacker compromises or an attacker was
worth his salt compromises that spare
laptop
he's gonna see AWS API creds and assume
he's hit the jackpot but the moment he
uses them our system effectively sends
that email to say someone just touched
the fake API keys that you said you are
storing on your spare laptop so so again
the whole idea with canary tokens much
like Canaries is a deploy in minutes or
seconds but a high fidelity message that
tells you that bad stuff is happening on
your network and we are so so
essentially that's our pitch what
interesting personal projects or events
do you have on the go currently hearing
so-so currently for the most part we've
just gotten back from a black hat and
DEF CON in Las Vegas so so we just
wrapping up some of the research that we
presented there some of it was was
around this token stuff currently we we
playing a fair bit on what new things
can beat okand and and some of them get
pretty ridiculous but an an idea from a
good friend of ours from Colin Molina
actually goes into can you start
progressively token in binaries to let
you know when those binaries are being
reverse engineered by people so so
figuring out that they've now hit stage
one so they found Canadia one but this
guy's actually gone a little further
he's now in the decryption algorithm so
he's managing to hit token to UM it's an
interesting idea and it's we've got a
few avenues for attack on it so so we're
playing a fair bit with that but for the
most part right now we kind of heads
down we've got a new release off of
canary coming out soon so keeping busy
and keeping out of trouble for the most
part we'll be asking people find out
more about you and what you do um so all
our canary stuff is on the horribly
chosen domain name canary tools
and people can find us there or at
thinks calm which is equally hard to
pronounce or they can follow me on
Twitter as hard on Mir do you have any
other recent podcasts or conference
talks that you think I would help our
listeners understand what he speaks of
network security we should be focusing
on yes so I've got to in a completely
horrible example of self-promotion I did
a talk at troopers a few years back
called the hard thing about hard things
that's a word spending the 45 minutes of
your life that you won't get back from
listening to if nothing else it paints
the picture of why the problem is as bad
as bad at it as it is and a follow-up
talk that I gave to that paints some
possible solutions for it at least some
directions for attack so so yeah if if
people want to be a little bit depressed
they they should check out the hard
thing about hard things which was the
troopers keynote and if they interested
in building products or building
solutions to help dig our way out of
this they can check out a talk that I
gave at t2 called make Defence great
again both of these are available on the
YouTube so I can drop your link after
this hearing thanks for joining us today
thanks so much thanks for having me for
software engineering radio this is kim
cardio a host
thanks for listening to se Radio an
educational program brought to you by
Triple E software magazine for more
about the podcast including other
episodes visit our website at SE - radio
net to provide feedback you can comment
on each episode on the website or reach
us on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter or
through our slack channel at SC
radio.com you can also email us at team
@ SC - radio net this and all other
episodes of SU radio is licensed under
Creative Commons license 2.5 thanks for
listening